Philip Yenawine Collection
Visual AIDS Archive
Philip Yenawine Collection
1988-1994
Visual AIDS Archive
1 Linear Feet
Biographical / Historical
Philip Yenawine has been engaged in museum education for forty years, ten of those as director of education at MoMA. While serving as the director of education at MoMA in the 1980s, he co-created Art Matters Foundation with Laura Donnelly in order to provide direct financial support to daring artists who made "art that mattered." As an early member of the Visual AIDS steering committee, Philip was integral to organizing the first years of Day Without Art and helping coordinate other Visual AIDS projects.
Philip also co-created Visual Thinking Strategies with Abigail Housen, a framework for art education that fosters collaborative, inclusive, and community-building dialogue. He continues to write about art, support the implementation of Visual Thinking Strategies, and to advise the board of Art Matters.
Scope and Contents
The Philip Yenawine Collection relates almost exclusively to Yenawine's work with Visual AIDS and allows for the detailed exploration of an early, coordinated arts-community response to the AIDS crisis. Materials span 1988-1995 and include correspondence, ephemera, meeting minutes and agendas, internal memos, and press releases. The collection preserves the logistics and efforts that turned intention into institutional actions, from nation-wide contact lists and participant rolls to day-of operating schedules, speeches, run-of-show documents, celebrity outreach, and post-event follow-up. Taken together they show Visual AIDS from the unique perspective of a participant-organizer capturing the work of coalition-building, messaging, logistics, and governance in the first six years of Visual AIDS. While much of the collection centers on Day Without Art, other materials help trace the evolution of Visual AIDS as an organization, including bylaws, budgets, fundraising proposals, and debates over priorities. Some related Visual AIDS projects represented in the collection include Night Without Light, Electric Blanket, and the Red Ribbon Project.
The collection is separated into two series: "MoMA and Day Without Art" and "Visual AIDS" according to which subject the materials more closely pertain.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection were chronologized but kept in original order as much as possible.
- MoMA and Day Without Art (1988-1991)
  Biographical / Historical
  This series consists primarily of materials pertaining to outreach about Day Without Art from 1989 to 1991, while Yenawine worked as the Director of Education at MoMA. He helped to coordinate the first year's observance and corresponded with other institutions to encourage their participation. His correspondence is extensive and well-represented in this series. It traces the evolution and reach of the first three years of Day Without Art through personal papers, press clippings, and ephemera.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of personal papers, press clippings, correspondence, ephemera, and photographic prints. These materials were created from 1988-1991.
  - Box 1, Folder 1: November 1988-February 1989 (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 2: March-August 1989 (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 3: September-October 1989 (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 4: November-December 1989 (Box 1)
  - Box 1, Folder 5: 1991 (Box 1)
- Visual AIDS (1988-1994)
  This series is focused on Yenawine's relationship with and role in Visual AIDS beyond his direct work with Day Without Art. This series does contain some Day Without Art papers but is more focused on Visual AIDS's development as an organization through meeting minutes, memos, press releases, ephemera, and internal correspondence. It traces the evolution of the organization over its first six years, from 1988 to 1994.
  This series consists of personal papers, correspondence, ephemera, press clippings, press kits, periodicals, and photographic prints. These materials were created from 1988-1994.
  - Box 2, Folder 1: 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 2: 1990 (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 3: Press Kits (1990) (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 4: January-April 1991 (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 5: May-December 1991 (Box 2)
  - Box 2, Folder 6: 1992-1994 (Box 2)